{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Members of this class established the Agrarian League to combat tariff reductions on grain imports. Often centered around estates in East Elbia, members of this class dominated the Herrenhaus, as well as agriculture in one region east of the River Elbe. The appointment of one member of this class as minister president heralded an era of “blood and iron,” and Otto von Bismarck was a member of this class, who owned estates worked by peasants. For ten points, name this class of Prussian landed aristocrats.",
      "answer": "Junkers"
    },
    {
      "question": "This movement was sparked by the criticism of Samuel Benton, a leader of Granville County, in George Sim's \"Nutbush Address,\" which criticized high taxes and corrupt officials who embezzled colonial funds. Leaders of this movement included Hermann Husband and Benjamin Merrill, a former militia captain. Members of this movement disbanded the court in Orange County, rioted in Hillsborough, and lost the Battle of Alamance to Governor William Tryon. For ten points, name this uprising of farmers in colonial North Carolina.",
      "answer": [
        "Regulator Movement",
        "Regulator Insurrection, War of Regulation,",
        "War of the Regulation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A song about a conflict known by this term calls the opposing side “plunderers…torturers of people” and is titled “The Sacred War.” Victory in one conflict sometimes known by this term was commemorated with the triumph of “God Save the Tsar” over “La Marseillaise” in Tchaikovsky’s 1812 Overture. As of 2015, Ukraine has officially replaced all mentions of a conflict known by this term with World War Two. For ten points, identify this propagandistic term used within the Soviet Union for the 1941 to 1945 conflict on the Eastern Front with Nazi Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "Great Patriotic War or Velikaya Otechestvennaya voyna",
        "Patriotic War of 1812",
        "prompt on “World War Two”",
        "“Eastern Front” before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person served as secretary of national defense during the presidency of Manuel Ávila Camacho. The IPN was a National Polytechnic Institute created during this person's tenure as president. 45 million acres of land were redistributed during the rule of this president, whose tenure coincided with the end of the Maximato, and this president's administration created the state-owned enterprise Pemex. For ten points, name this president of Mexico from 1934 to 1940 who nationalized his country's oil industry.",
      "answer": "Lázaro Cárdenas or Lázaro Cárdenas del Río 1 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "question": "A dissertation that this author wrote while attending Trinity College eventually was expanded into the work The Growth of Plato's Ideal Theory. A waxing and waning moon and a serpent that sheds its skin are among the categories of tales that this man examined across societies in a book by this man subtitled \"A Study in Magic and Religion,\" which is named for an object from the Aeneid. For ten points, name this sociologist who wrote a study of magic and religion called The Golden Bough.",
      "answer": "James Frazer or Sir James George Frazer"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Bouyei myth, this figure married the daughter of the Dragon King, becoming the ancestor of humanity. After being born, this figure grew ten feet every day for thousands of years, pushing the heavens upward the whole time. This figure was born after Yin and Yang balanced within a giant cosmic egg after incubating for 18,000 years. After his death, the fleas on this figure’s body became the animals of the world. For ten points, name this giant and creator deity from Chinese mythology.",
      "answer": "Pangu ]"
    },
    {
      "question": "The four Dawes brothers, including the namesake of the Dawes Plan, were all born in this city and enriched by a namesake oil boom. The Putnam Street Bridge connected this city to Fort Harmar as the earliest free crossing on the Muskingum River. This city lends its name to a set of Hopewell-style \"Earthworks,\" and this earliest settlement in the Northwest Territory was named to honor French assistance in the American Revolution. For ten points, identify this Ohio city named for the wife of Louis the Sixteenth.",
      "answer": "Marietta"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person is known for having an influence on Irving Kahn, who named a son after this person. This person coined terms such as \"margin of safety\" and \"Mr. Market\" in one work, and this person, who was known for advocating index funds, also had a strong influence on Charlie Munger. This person is considered the \"father of value investing,\" and, with David Dodd, this person authored the book Security Analysis. For ten points, name this British-American economist and teacher of Warren Buffet, who authored The Intelligent Investor.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Graham or Benjamin Grossbaum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Members of this nation attacked the 478th Civil Affairs Battalion using hand-thrown projectiles such as water balloons. This nation was founded by Mayor Dennis Wardlow, who claimed the people of this nation would have “seceded…where others have failed.” The prime minister of this nation declared war against the United States shortly after inauguration by breaking a loaf of Cuban bread, and this nation attempted to annex the Seven Mile Bridge and forcibly reopen Dry Tortugas National Park. For ten points, identify this micronation which was formed in protest of Border Control blockades in Key West.",
      "answer": "Conch Republic 2 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "question": "One person of this surname served as chair of the Atomic Energy Commission before becoming secretary of defense in 1973. The term \"imperial presidency\" was popularized by a person with this surname who, while serving in the OSS, wrote The Age of Jackson. That person with this surname won a 1966 Pulitzer Prize for the work A Thousand Days, which was based on experiences as special assistant to John F. Kennedy. For ten points, identify this surname of two American historians named Arthur.",
      "answer": [
        "Schlesinger",
        "James Rodney Schlesinger, Arthur Meier Schlesinger Jr., Arthur Bancroft Schlesinger,",
        "Arthur Meier Schlesinger Sr."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler dispatched the general Zhang Fu to conquer the Hồ dynasty, leading to the annexation of Vietnam as Jiaozhi Province. This ruler aimed to compile knowledge in a namesake \"Encyclopedia,\" and, during the Jingnan Rebellion, this ruler seized the throne from his the Jianwen Emperor. This emperor moved the imperial capital to Beijing and initiated the construction of the Forbidden City. For ten points, name this third emperor of the Ming Dynasty who sponsored the voyages of explorer Zheng He.",
      "answer": [
        "Yongle Emperor",
        "Emperor Chengzu of Ming, Zhu Di, Yongle Encyclopedia,",
        "Yongle Dadian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Stesagoras was the predecessor of this politician as tyrant of Chersonese. This politician was named after a champion at Olympic chariot racing, and a son of this politician rose to prominence for his actions at the Battle of Salamis. Ciimon was a son of this politician, who was elected strategoi in 490 B.C.E., in which capacity this leader helped defeat Achaemenid forces during the invasion of Greece. For ten points, name this Athenian statesman best-known for leading the victorious forces at the Battle of Marathon.",
      "answer": "Miltiades the Younger 3 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was called the \"most influential Southerner in Congress between Calhoun and Lyndon Johnson.\" During World War Two, the press referred to this New Deal advocate as the “Assistant President” for leading the Office of War Mobilization. This politician was named Time’s Man of the Year in 1946 after rejecting the Morgenthau Plan, and this person headed the Office of Economic Stabilization after serving the shortest Supreme Court tenure in history. For ten points, identify this postwar secretary of state and governor of South Carolina.",
        "answer": "James Francis Byrnes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Byrnes was preceded as secretary of state by this former chair of U.S. Steel and administrator of the Lend-Lease Program, who resigned as secretary to become the first U.S. ambassador to the United Nations.",
        "answer": "Edward Reilly Stettinius Jr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader sent a eunuch to teach Greek letters and etiquette to her son’s Frankish betrothed, Rotrude, in 781 C.E.. After opposition to femineum imperium led Leo the Third to crown another Imperator Romanorum, this ruler was asked “to join in marriage and unite East and West” in 802 C.E. This ruler's people tolerated losses to the Abbasids and the blinding and imprisonment of Constantine the Sixth, but her possible marriage to Charlemagne led to her replacement by Nicephorus the First. For ten points, name this only reigning Byzantine empress.",
        "answer": [
          "Irene of Athens",
          "Sarantapechaena"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Irene's original husband, Leo the Fourth, was a vocal supporter of this Byzantine movement which aimed to destroy religious imagery as idolatrous.",
        "answer": [
          "Iconoclasm",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The overthrow of this leader began an era known as the Infamous Decade. This leader, who led failed 1893 and 1905 revolutions to overthrow the regimes of Julio Roca's National Autonomists, was finally elected president following the passage of the Sáenz Peña Law. This president served two terms, which were interrupted by the Marcelo de Alvear administration and ended with Jose Uriburu's rebellion. For ten points, name this first democratically elected president of Argentina.",
        "answer": "Hipólito Yrigoyen or Juan Hipólito del Sagrado Corazón de Jesús Yrigoyen"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Yrigoyen was buried at La Recoleta Cemetery in Buenos Aires, the resting place of this president of Argentina from 1983 to 1989 who served as the first democratically elected president after the post-Perón National Reorganization Process.",
        "answer": "Raúl Alfonsín or Raúl Ricardo Alfonsín 4 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this event, the correct \"squawk\" code was given and the signal \"REQUEST RADIATION ASSIGN\" was pushed 22 times. The Fogarty Report studied this event, which involved a \"RoboCruiser\" deploying the Aegis System under William Rogers. Ronald Reagan declared a written note to be an apology in this event, which was the deadliest disaster of its type until Malaysia Airlines Flight 17 was downed. For ten points, identify this 1988 event, which involved an aircraft flying from Tehran to Dubai being mistakenly destroyed by the USS Vincennes.",
        "answer": [
          "Shoot-down of Iran Air Flight 655",
          "descriptive answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earlier in the Iran-Iraq War, this American ship was attacked by two Iraqi Exocet missiles in the Persian Gulf.",
        "answer": "USS Stark"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The antagonist of this poem is defeated after being caught menstruating, inspiring her enemy to guard her retreat in an act of mercy. After forcing the pregnant goddess Macha into a footrace, a city in this poem is cursed to have all of its men afflicted with the pangs of childbirth in its hour of need. The events of this poem are sparked by a dispute between King Ailill and his wife over who is wealthier. For ten points, identify this Irish epic that depicts the victory of Cú Chulainn over Queen Medb.",
        "answer": [
          "The Tain or Táin Bó Cúailnge",
          "The Cattle Raid of Cooley"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Throughout The Tain, Cú Chulainn is harassed by this goddess of fate, who is often depicted as a triple goddess accompanied by crows or ravens.",
        "answer": "Morrigan or Morrígu"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Disgruntled members of one of these organizations formed the Confrerie Pictura. Rogier van der Weyden depicted the patron saint of one of these organizations making a drawing of the Virgin Mary. One of these organizations named for Saint Luke admitted Judith Leyster in Haarlem. One member of these organizations, Willem van Doeyenburg, is a central figure in a painting that was once hung in a staathof and depicts a group of syndics appraising a sample of cloth. For ten points, identify these commonly depicted European labor organizations which managed specific crafts and trade.",
        "answer": [
          "guilds",
          "Guild of Saint Luke",
          "Syndics of the Drapers’ Guild"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the Netherlands, guilds held significant influence under local government officials, such as the holder of this title, which is roughly synonymous with mayor. This title was once held by Frans Banninck Cocq, the central subject of Rembrandt’s The Night Watch.",
        "answer": [
          "burgemeester or burgermeister",
          "or burgomaster 5 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Authorities created a police force called the \"Specials\" to combat this event, which culminated in violence on \"Bloody Saturday.\" This event began when building and metal trades workers walked off their jobs, with approximately 30,000 workers participating. The Citizens' Committee of 1,000 opposed this 1919 labor action and published a newspaper that called organizers \"alien scum.\" For ten points, name this six-week Canadian labor protest, one of North America's largest general strikes.",
        "answer": [
          "Winnipeg General Strike",
          "Winnipeg alone after \"general strikes\" is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In another act of defiance, impoverished Canadians who were feeling the squeeze of the Great Depression created these alliterative, horse-drawn automobiles, which were named after the prime minister they blamed for their economic hardship.",
        "answer": "Bennett Buggies"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This opera inspired Letitia Elizabeth Landon's poem \"Fenella's Escape.\" Audience members allegedly walked out during this opera's duet \"Amour sacré de la patrie,\" which took place during a festival celebrating King William the First's 15th year of rule. This opera's plot details an uprising against foreign rule, and it debuted in Brussels. For ten points, identify this opera by Daniel Auber, which supposedly signaled the beginning of the 1830 Belgian Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "La muette de Portici ] or The Mute Girl of Portici",
          "or The Dumb Girl of Portici",
          "Masaniello ]"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the characters in The Mute Girl of Portici is the fisherman Masaniello, who led a 1647 revolt in this Italian city against the Habsburgs.",
        "answer": [
          "Naples or Napoli",
          "Neapolitan Revolt of 1647"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person was the only Democratic senator to not vote for the Dodd-Frank Act, and this politician was also the only senator to vote against the Patriot Act. This politician was unseated by Ron Johnson, and one act named for this politician included the Stand by Your Ad provision, which required candidates to say \"I approve this message.” With John McCain, this politician was one of the two chief sponsors of the Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act. For ten points, name this senator from Wisconsin who served in office from 1993 to 2011.",
        "answer": "Russ Feingold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Feingold lost his seat to Republican Ron John in 2011, who has been joined in the Senate by this Democrat, who replaced the retiring Herb Kohl, becoming the first woman elected from Wisconsin and the first openly LGBT senator.",
        "answer": "Tammy Baldwin or Tammy Suzanne Green 6 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, prisoners were freed from Newgate Prison before it was burned, and this event included attacks on the homes of Lord Chief Justice Mansfield and the Earl of Sandwich. King George the Third personally ordered troops to fire on rioters to end this event, which was led by a nobleman who later converted to Judaism. This event began after a petition to repeal Savile's Act, or the Papists Act of 1778. For ten points, name these 1780 London riots named after a certain Lord George, which targeted Catholics.",
        "answer": "Gordon Riots"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Gordon Riots, soldiers were stationed at this major institution, which was founded in 1694 and is known as \"The Old Lady of Threadneedle Street.\"",
        "answer": "Bank of England"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Hawaii",
      "prompt": "Concerning the history of Hawaii, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Tropical fruit that was the principal export of the plantation economy, a now common topping on Hawaiian pizza.",
          "answer": "pineapple"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fruit company named for James, whose cousin, Sanford, became the first territorial governor of Hawaii.",
          "answer": [
            "Dole Company",
            "James Dole",
            "Sanford Dole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which Hawaii was annexed by the U.S., the same year as the start of the Spanish-American War.",
          "answer": "1898"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitution named for a pointed addition to a rifle, signed by King Kalakaua and giving power to white Hawaiians.",
          "answer": "Bayonet Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Final queen of Hawaii, who was overthrown in 1893 by the Committee of Safety.",
          "answer": "Liliʻuokalani or Lydia Liliʻu Loloku Walania Kamakaʻeha"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the first Protestants to bring Christianity to the Hawaiian islands, whose namesake grandson rediscovered Machu Picchu.",
          "answer": [
            "Hiram Bingham",
            "Hiram Bingham the First",
            "Hiram Bingham the Third"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Medal of Honor recipient, the highest ranking Asian-American in history, who served Hawaii in the Senate from 1963 to 2012.",
          "answer": [
            "Daniel Inouye ] or Daniel Ken Inouye",
            "phonetic pronunciations"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Jewish doctor from Pennsylvania who was elected governor of Hawaii in 2022.",
          "answer": "Josh Green or Joshua Booth Green 8"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Counter-Reformation",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Counter-Reformation, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title held by Paul the Third, the first leader of the Counter-Reformation, and head of the Catholic Church.",
          "answer": [
            "pope",
            "papacy, bishop of Rome, supreme pontiff, Roman pontiff,",
            "sovereign pontiff"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "German monk who started the Protestant Reformation by nailing the 95 Theses to a church door.",
          "answer": "Martin Luther"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for the Catholic judicial process of combating heresy, the Spanish example of which was notably brutal.",
          "answer": [
            "inquisition",
            "Spanish Inquisition"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Given name of two Catholic monarchs, one of whom was \"Queen of Scots\" and one who was nicknamed \"Bloody.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Mary",
            "Mary, Queen of Scots, Mary Stuart, Mary the First, Mary Tudor",
            "Bloody Mary"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English statesman and saint, who was beheaded in 1535 for refusing to accept the king as head of the Church of England.",
          "answer": "Thomas More"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ecumenical council, held in Northern Italy from 1545 to 1563, which launched the Counter Reformation.",
          "answer": "Council of Trent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish city, in Castile and León, where Francisco Suarez led a namesake school of scholastic philosophy.",
          "answer": [
            "Salamanca",
            "School of Salamanca"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mystic nun who reformed the Carmelite order and wrote The Interior Castle and The Way of Perfection.",
          "answer": [
            "Teresa of Avila or Saint Teresa of Jesus",
            "or Teresa Sanchez de Cepeda Davila y Ahumada 9"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Afghanistan",
      "prompt": "Concerning the history of Afghanistan, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Terrorist attack in New York City that sparked an American invasion of Afghanistan in 2001.",
          "answer": "9/11 or September Eleventh attacks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Natural material naming a trading \"road\" that connected Afghanistan to Eastern China and Europe.",
          "answer": [
            "silk",
            "Silk Road"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Jihadist group that ruled Afghanistan from 1996 to 2001 and again since 2021.",
          "answer": [
            "Taliban",
            "Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City that has been the capital since it was moved from Kandahar in 1776.",
          "answer": "Kabul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire that fought with the UK for influence over Afghanistan in the 19th century \"Great Game.\"",
          "answer": "Russian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primary city of western Afghanistan, the 1856 capture of which led to the Anglo-Persian War.",
          "answer": "Herat"
        },
        {
          "question": "Iranic ethnic group, most of whom live in Pakistan, who were known as \"Afghans\" until 1964.",
          "answer": [
            "Pashtun or Pakhtun",
            "or Pathan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Father of modern Afghanistan,\" whose eponymous empire ruled until 1823.",
          "answer": [
            "Ahmad Shah Durrani or Ahmad Shah Abdali",
            "Durrani Empire 10"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Systems of Survival, this thinker described conflicting “moral syndromes” named for “guardians” and “commerce.” In 1979, this thinker argued for Quebec independence in a Massey Lecture that was later turned into the book The Question of Separatism. While advocating for preserving Greenwich Village, (20 pts)",
        "this thinker claimed that the “urban renewal” and “slum clearance” policies of Robert Moses were contrary to New Yorkers' needs. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this American urban planner who wrote The Death and Life of Great American Cities."
      ],
      "answer": "Jane Jacobs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The orator of this speech claimed \"we will be able to overcome in the future by a superior mechanical force.\" It wasn't given by a British politician, but the radio services of the BBC broadcast this speech, which was less widely heard than a similar speech delivered four days later. Georges Mathieu (20 pts)",
        "designed a postage stamp to commemorate the 70th anniversary of this 1940 speech, which is often seen as the inspiration of the French resistance. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this speech given by Charles de Gaulle on a certain summer day."
      ],
      "answer": "Appeal of 18 June or June 18th or L'Appel du 18 juin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following the death of Francisco Ferrer, this person was made captain-general of the city of Barcelona in October 1909. This soldier, who was a colonel under Arsenio Martínez Campos during the Ten Years' War, adopted a policy regarding reconcentrados that is thought to have resulted in (20 pts)",
        "hundreds of thousands of deaths on one island. Under Alfonso the Thirteenth, this person served as governor-general of Cuba from 1896 to 1897. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this administrator during the Spanish-American War, nicknamed 'The Butcher.'"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Valeriano Weyler or Valeriano Weyler y Nicolau",
        "Butcher Weyler",
        "First Duke of Rubí",
        "First Marquess of Tenerife"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The town of Oderzo was razed during this conflict following the Battle of Carnuntum, after which a relief effort by Titus Furius Victorinus was quashed. This conflict involved the Sarmatian (20 pts)",
        "Iazyges tribe, who killed the governor of Moesia, Marcus Claudius Fronto, and this conflict led to the rise of Claudius Pompeianus, who would later refuse the imperial throne three times. Coinciding with the writing of The (10 pts)",
        "Meditations, for ten points, what was this conflict fought along the Danube against a namesake Germanic tribe waged for over a decade by Roman emperor Marcus Aurelius?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Marcomannic Wars",
        "bellum Germanicum et Sarmaticum",
        "but"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician was nominated by Bill Clinton to be an ambassador to China, but was blocked due to opposition from Jesse Helms and Edwin Meese. This politician challenged John Kerry in a 1996 Senate election for his seat, and this politician was the only person to win a delegate in the 2020 Republican presidential primaries (20 pts)",
        "against Donald Trump. Part of the most successful Libertarian presidential ticket in history, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, who is this former governor of Massachusetts from 1991 to 1997, who served as Gary Johnson's running mate in 2016?"
      ],
      "answer": "Bill Weld William Floyd Weld 11 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2018, this group began receiving support from the Wagner Group in exchange for granting Russia access to a certain country’s gold deposits. This group has carried out the ongoing Masalit Massacres, which have killed over 10,000 civilians. This United Arab Emirates-backed (20 pts)",
        "group evolved from Arabized Janjaweed militias in the Darfur region, where they have been accused of committing genocide against Christian Africans. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this paramilitary force led by Hemedti in a brutal civil war against the Sudanese government."
      ],
      "answer": "RSF"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A never-removed bullet wound was received by Joshua Barney during this battle, in which he led 480 troops that engaged in hand-to-hand fighting. A nephew of Levin Winder named William was the commander of American troops at this battle, which was described as \"the greatest disgrace ever dealt to (20 pts)",
        "American arms.\" The flight of one side after this battle came to be known as its namesake \"races.\" A defeat for the Regular Army, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, what 1814 battle allowed the British to burn the White House?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Bladensburg",
        "Bladensburg Races"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this family by marriage was the sister of Robert Gould Shaw and first woman to hold public office in New York City, and another member of this family was a U.S. Ambassador to Spain and wrote The Biglow Papers and A Fable for Critics before becoming the first editor of The (20 pts)",
        "Atlantic Monthly. A member of this family, Francis Cabot, named a textile town established by the (10 pts)",
        "Boston Associates in Middlesex County. For ten points, name this prominent Brahmin family whose name graces a major industrial town of mid-19th century Massachusetts."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Lowell",
        "Josephine Shaw Lowell, James Russell Lowell,",
        "Francis Cabot Lowell"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This person wrote Through the Caucasus to the Volga, which was inspired travels to Armenia. Observations made by this explorer during provided data for the development of the concept of the Ekman Spiral. During the 1920s and 1930s, an International Office for Refugees (20 pts)",
        "named for this explorer issued namesake passports to stateless refugees. The Fram expedition led by this explorer made use of a ship that would later be employed by countryman (10 pts)",
        "Roald Amundsen. For ten points, name this Norwegian explorer and Nobel Peace Prize laureate who attempted to reach the North Pole."
      ],
      "answer": "Fridtjof Nansen"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure fought against the Bolsheviks in the Soviet Union after his father, an Orthodox priest, was recalled from the United States, and this White Russian was one of the few to live to see the fall of the Berlin Wall. This American (20 pts)",
        "intelligence officer headed a mission to investigate German nuclear capabilities, and this person led the exploratory Alsos Mission. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, identify this officer who reported that Oppenheimer “may still be connected with the Communist Party” during an investigation highlighted in a 2023 film."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Boris Pash or Boris Theodore Pash",
        "Boris Fedorovich Pashkovsky 12 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 16"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure is associated with a golden kite, which is said to have landed on a bow called a kinshikyū. A holiday known as Kigensetsu honors the ascension of this figure on February Eleventh. This figure is said to have led an “Eastern Expedition,” which captured the city of (20 pts)",
        "Yamato, and this figure, whose rule is preceded by the Age of the Gods, is said to be the grandson of the sun goddess Amaterasu. Discussed in chapter three of the Nihon Shoki, (10 pts)",
        "for ten points, who is this mythical first emperor of Japan?"
      ],
      "answer": "Emperor Jimmu"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This house merged with the Saxe-Coburg line through the marriage of Maria the Second to Ferdinand the Second. This dynasty established its colonial capital at Rio de Janeiro after fleeing Napoleonic forces (20 pts)",
        "with British help in 1807. The last monarch of this dynasty, Manuel the Second, was overthrown in the 1910 republican revolution. (10 pts)",
        "João the Sixth was a ruler of, for ten points, what royal house that ruled Portugal from 1640 to 1910 and independent Brazil until 1889, following the House of Aviz?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "House of Braganza or Casa de Bragança",
        "Brigantine dynasty",
        "dinastia Brigantina"
      ]
    }
  ]
}